Williams Obstetrics.
Chapter 64: Psychiatric Disorders.
Psychological Adjustments To Pregnancy Classification Of Psychiatric Disorders Major Depression Bipolar And Related Disorders Anxiety Disorders Schizophrenia Spectrum Disorders Eating Disorders Substance Use Disorder Posttraumatic Stress Disorders Personality Disorders References Pregnancy and the puerperium are at times sufficiently stressful to provoke mental illness.
Such illness may represent recurrence or exacerbation of a preexisting psychiatric disorder, or it may signal the onset of a new condition.
Especially prevalent in pregnancy and the puerperium are depressive and anxiety disorders .
Many of these disorders are associated with less prenatal care, substance use, preterm delivery, and other poor obstetrical and neonatal outcomes.
In affected gravidas, the postpartum psychiatric illness rate also is higher .
Last, perinatal mood disorders can adversely hinder the mother-child relationship.
Despite these known risks, obstetrical providers often are reluctant to confront or fail to identify mental health issues during pregnancy.
Lyell and colleagues (2012) found that the diagnosis of depression was not documented in nearly half of the records of affected women.
Psychological Adjustments To Pregnancy.
Biochemical factors and life stressors can markedly influence mental health and mental illness during the perinatal period .
Intuitively, pregnancy exacerbates some coexisting psychological disorders.
Namely, a higher risk for mood disorders is linked with pregnancy-related shifts in sex steroid and monoamine neurotransmitter levels, dysfunction of the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axis, thyroid dysfunction, and immune response alterations .
These changes, coupled with familial clustering of depression cases, suggest that a subgroup of women may be at greater risk for developing a unipolar major depressive disorder during pregnancy.
Women respond variably to the stresses of pregnancy.
Some express persistent concerns regarding fetal health, child care, lifestyle changes, or fear of childbirth pain.
Anxiety, sleep disorders, and functional impairment are common (Romero, 2014; Vythilingum, 2008).
The level of perceived stress is significantly higher for women whose fetus is at high risk for a malformation, for those with preterm labor or delivery, and for those with other medical complications (Alder, 2007; Ross, 2006).
For example, Hippman and associates (2009) screened for depression in 81 women who had an increased risk for a fetus with aneuploidy.
Half of these women had a positive depression screening score, whereas only 2.4 percent of those with a normal pregnancy did so.
Several steps can diminish psychological stress in the event of a poor obstetrical outcome.
For example, following a stillbirth, parental contact with the newborn and provision of photographs and other infant memorabilia is encouraged .
Addressing associated sleep disorders also seems reasonable .
# The Puerperium.
This is a particularly stressful time for women, and risks for mental illness are increased.
Up to 15 percent of women develop a nonpsychotic postpartum depressive disorder within 6 months of delivery (Tam, 2007; Yonkers, 2011).
Depressive disorders are more likely in women with obstetrical complications such as severe preeclampsia or fetal-growth restriction, especially if associated with early delivery.
Prior psychiatric disorders or childhood trauma also raises the risk for postpartum depression .
Instead, some have a psychotic illness following delivery, and half of these manifest as a bipolar disorder.
Importantly, stressors beyond those directly related to the pregnancy also can raise perinatal depression rates.
Tarney and colleagues (2015) identified spouse military deployment as a factor for postpartum depression.
But, among women with a history of bipolar disorder, these elements play a lesser role in the development of mania or depression .
Maternity Blues Also called postpartum blues, this is a time-limited period of heightened emotional reactivity experienced by
half of women within the first week after parturition.
Prevalence estimates for the blues range from 26 to 84 percent depending on diagnostic criteria (O’Hara, 2014).
This emotional state generally peaks on the fourth or fifth postpartum day and normalizes by day 10 (O’Keane, 2011).
The predominant mood during the puerperium is happiness, but affected mothers are more emotionally labile.
They also may have insomnia, weepiness, depression, anxiety, poor concentration, and irritability.
Mothers may be transiently tearful for several hours and then recover completely, only to be tearful again the next day.
Supportive treatment is indicated, and affected women are reassured that the dysphoria is transient and most likely due to biochemical changes.
They are monitored for development of depression and other severe psychiatric disturbances.
# Perinatal Evaluation and Screening.
Both the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2018b) and the United States Preventive Services Task Force now recommend screening at least once during the perinatal period for depression and anxiety .
Indeed, it has recently been recommended that all obstetrical care providers complete a full assessment of mood and emotional well-being during the comprehensive postpartum visit .
Identification of psychiatric disorders in pregnancy can be challenging because changes in behavior and mood are often attributed to pregnancy.
To differentiate these, Yonkers and associates (2011) recommend assessment of cognitive symptoms—for example, loss of concentration.
Excessive anxiety and insomnia—even during periods of infant sleep—also can suggest postpartum depression.
Specific factors for depression are reviewed and include a prior personal or family history of depression.
Universal screening programs for depression continue to evolve .
One major step forward is state-level support for screening.
Beginning July 1, 2018, mothers who take newborns for Texas Health Steps routine examination are able to receive testing and counseling .
At Parkland Hospital, mental illness screening is completed at the first prenatal visit using a brief riskbased query and again postpartum using a recognized screening tool for postpartum depression.
Questions search for psychiatric disorders, related therapy, prior or current use of psychoactive medications, and current symptoms.
Women with a history of sexual, physical, or verbal abuse; illicit substance use; and personality disorders are also at greater risk for depression .
Smoking and nicotine dependence and obesity also raise rates of all mental disorders in pregnancy .
Last, because eating disorders may be exacerbated by pregnancy, affected women are followed closely (p. 1149).
Several screening instruments shown in Table 64-1 are available and have been validated for use during pregnancy and the puerperium .
Use of one of these is encouraged because symptom- or risk-based screening alone may be insufficient.
Cerimele and colleagues (2013) found that obstetrician-gynecologists failed to identify 60 percent of depressed women in clinical practice.
In one study at Parkland Hospital, 17,000 women were screened during their first postpartum visit using the Edinburgh Postnatal Depression Scale (EPDS).
Of these, 6 percent had scores that indicated either minor or major depressive symptoms, and 12 women had thoughts of self-harm .
In another study, Kim and coworkers (2015) assessed suicidal ideation in more than 22,000 women screened using the EPDS both during pregnancy and postpartum.
They found rates of depression as high as 3.4 percent during the puerperium.
A small fraction of those with thoughts of self-harm had a credible plan, intent, and means for attempted suicide.
Table 64-1.
Depression Screening Tools Screening for perinatal depression alone was previously considered insufficient, however, evidence now suggests that screening itself has clinical benefit .
One systematic review of six randomized trials that screened pregnant or postpartum women found that follow-up of these women weeks to months later
demonstrated an absolute risk reduction in the depression rate by a range of 2.1 to 9.1 percent (O’Connor, 2016).
However, this review included studies with and without treatment components compared with usual care.
Another limitation is that four of the six studies did not exclude women previously known to be depressed.
Findings from this analysis prompted an interim update by the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2018b) to state that screening alone can have clinical benefit, although treatment initiation or referral to a mental health care provider offers maximum benefit.
Mechanisms to ensure adequate ensuing care can be problematic.
Nelson and associates (2013) found that more than three fourths of the 1106 women with abnormally elevated EPDS scores did not keep their later appointment for more formal psychiatric evaluation.
Barriers include access to care, personal perception of depression, and societal stigmata.
Women referred to a behavioral health provider located at the same site as their obstetrical care are four times more likely to access treatment than those referred elsewhere .
To take advantage of this, at Parkland Hospital, mental health counselors also practice at postpartum clinic sites.
Other promising interventions for puerperal depression include home visits, telephone-based peer support, and interpersonal psychotherapy (Dennis, 2013; Lavender, 2013; Yonemoto, 2017).
A report from Kaiser Permanente, which describes the benefits and hurdles of system-based perinatal mental health care, provides a glimpse into the possible future of universal perinatal screening and treatment (Avalos, 2016; Flanagan, 2016).
# Treatment Considerations.
Once a positive mental health screen result is identified, a stage-based response protocol is triggered .
In brief, the initial response focuses on maternal and infant safety, and if possible, onsite patient assessment by either a mental health provider or mental health counselor.
Integrating on-site assessment and access to counselors quadruples later attendance rates to mental health appointments .
For women with suicidal or homicidal ideation, perinatal care providers first determine a working diagnosis.
Second, emergency psychiatric consultation is sought and ambulance transport is implemented if needed.
Concurrently, perinatal care and psychiatric teams ideally communicate closely.
Last, the patient, her family, and clinical staff are emotionally supported.
Appreciation for this issue’s significance has grown with the recent national emphasis on maternal mortality.
For example, Palladino and associates (2011) found that pregnancy-associated homicide and suicide were significant contributors to maternal mortality in a multistate sample from the National Violent Death Reporting system.
Many psychiatric disorders can be improved with counseling and psychotherapy.
In some instances, medications are needed.
Shared decision making is employed by patients and their health-care providers.
In particular, women taking psychotropic medication are informed of likely side effects.
Many of these drugs are discussed in Chapter 8, and some are discussed subsequently.
# Pregnancy Outcomes.
As noted, maternal psychiatric illness can be linked to untoward outcomes such as preterm birth, low birthweight, and perinatal mortality (Grigoriadis, 2013; Jarde, 2016; Steinberg, 2014).
In a study of 16,334 deliveries, a significant association between posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD) and spontaneous preterm delivery was identified .
Domestic abuse —another aforementioned risk factor for perinatal mood disorder—also is linked with adverse perinatal outcomes .
Classification Of Psychiatric Disorders.
The Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, Fifth Edition (DSM-5) is the most recent version from the American Psychiatric Association (2013).
The manual assists in classifying mental disorders and specifies criteria for each diagnosis.
It is presumed that correct diagnosis leads to specific treatment.
Mood Disorders.
Historically, depressive disorders
include major depression—a unipolar disorder—and manic-depression—a bipolar disorder with both manic and depressive episodes.
It also includes dysthymia, which is chronic, mild depression.
# Major Depression.
This is the most common depressive disorder, and the 12-month prevalence of major depressive episodes among adult women is 8.2 percent .
From 2011 to 2014, 16 percent of women had used an antidepressant in the prior month .
The diagnosis is made by identifying symptoms listed in Table 64-2, but very few patients manifest all of these.
Table 64-2.
Symptoms of Depressive Illnessa Major depression is multifactorial and prompted by genetic and environmental factors.
Families of affected individuals often also have members suffering with alcohol abuse and anxiety disorders.
Provocative conditions leading to depression include substance abuse, certain medications, other medical disorders, and life events that prompt grief reactions.
Although life events can trigger depression, genes influence the response to these events and render the distinction between genetic and environmental factors difficult.
Pregnancy and Depression Pregnancy is a major life stressor that can precipitate or exacerbate depressive tendencies.
In addition, various pregnancy-induced effects are implicated.
Hormones certainly affect mood, as evidenced by premenstrual syndrome and menopausal depression.
Estrogen has been linked to enhanced serotonin synthesis, decreased serotonin breakdown, and serotonin-receptor modulation .
Concordantly, women who experience postpartum depression often have higher predelivery serum estrogen and progesterone levels and experience a greater decline postpartum .
The prevalence of antenatal depression averaged 11 percent in one Cochrane Database review .
In more than 1800 women enrolled for prenatal care at a single clinic, Melville and coworkers (2010) found rates of nearly 10 percent.
A higher rate has been seen in those after antepartum complications .
Postpartum Depression Major or minor depression develops postpartum in 10 to 20 percent of women .
Postpartum depressive symptoms are associated with young maternal age, antenatal depression, unmarried status, smoking, newborns requiring intensive care, and stressors during pregnancy (Ko, 2017; Silverman, 2017).
Specifically, physical or verbal abuse is a potent risk for postpartum depression .
Last, serious adverse obstetrical events, especially those involving the neonate, are strongly linked (Nelson, 2013, 2015).
Depression is frequently recurrent.
Up to 70 percent of women with previous postpartum depression have a subsequent episode.
Women with both prior puerperal depression and a current episode of “maternity blues” carry an inordinately high risk for major depression.
Indeed, 2 to 9 months postpartum, assistance with postpartum depression was the fourth most common challenge identified in women in the Pregnancy Risk Assessment Monitoring System—PRAMS .
Postpartum depression is generally underrecognized and undertreated.
Major depression during pregnancy or after delivery can have devastating consequences for affected women, their children, and families.
One of the most significant contributions to the mortality rate among new mothers is suicide, which is most frequent among women with mental illness (Koren, 2012; Palladino, 2011).
If left untreated, up to 25 percent of women with postpartum depression will be depressed 1 year later.
As the duration of depression increases, so too does the number of sequelae and their severity.
Maternal depression during the first weeks and months after delivery can lead to insecure attachment and later behavioral problems in the child (Mezzacappa, 2017; Viktorin, 2017).
Depression Treatment Therapy for mood disorders during pregnancy and postpartum has evolved.
Babbitt (2014) and Pozzi (2014) and their associates have reviewed principles of perinatal care of women with major mental disorders.
In general, for mild and mild-moderate depression, psychological treatment options, such as cognitive behavioral therapy, are
considered first .
Light- to moderate-intensity exercise may be beneficial .
Antidepressant medications together with some form of psychotherapy are indicated for moderate to severe depression during pregnancy or the puerperium .
Shown in Figure 64-1 is one algorithm regarding mood disorder treatment.
Some of these medications are listed in Table 64-3.
For women with severe depression, a selective serotonin-reuptake inhibitor (SSRI) is selected initially.
If depressive symptoms improve during a 6-week trial, the medication is continued for a minimum of 6 months to prevent relapse .
Figure 64-1.
Treatment algorithm for pregnant women with mood disorders.
Rx = prescription.
Table 64-3.
Drugs Used for Treatment of Major Mood Disorders in Pregnant Women If the response is suboptimal or a relapse occurs, another SSRI is substituted, or psychiatric referral is considered.
At least 60 percent of women taking antidepressant medication before pregnancy have symptoms during pregnancy.
In one study, approximately three fourths of women taking antidepressants before pregnancy stopped taking them before or during early pregnancy .
For those who discontinue treatment, almost 70 percent have a relapse compared with approximately 25 percent who continue therapy.
In one metaanalysis, women using antidepressants during pregnancy had higher rates of preterm birth and low-birthweight neonates .
Some of the included studies failed to control for the underlying depressive illness .
Nevertheless, in their review, Ray and Stowe (2014) concluded that the relative reproductive safety data are reassuring and that antidepressants remain a reasonable treatment option.
Furthermore, recurrence sometime after medication is discontinued develops in 50 to 85 percent of women with an initial postpartum depressive episode.
Surveillance includes monitoring for thoughts of suicide or infanticide, emergence of psychosis, and response to therapy.
For some women, the course of illness is severe enough to warrant hospitalization.
Fetal and Neonatal Effects of Therapy.
Some known and possible fetal and neonatal effects of treatment are listed in Table 64-3.
Some studies suggest that SSRIs pose an elevated teratogenic risk for fetal cardiac defects, and these have mainly focused on paroxetine (Paxil).
Associations were most consistent for ventricular septal defects.
The estimated risk is no greater than 1 case in 200 exposed newborns .
Nevertheless, the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2018b) recommends that paroxetine be avoided in women who are either pregnant or planning pregnancy.
In women exposed to paroxetine in the first trimester, fetal echocardiography is considered.
In one analysis of SSRIs, exposure to SSRIs during pregnancy and perinatal mortality were not linked .
Andersen and associates (2014) found that women discontinuing SSRI treatment in early pregnancy had a small increased risk of miscarriage.
However, the risk was similar to that in women discontinuing SSRI treatment months before pregnancy.
These investigators concluded that treatment with SSRIs during pregnancy should not be discontinued for fear of miscarriage.
Of other potential effects, the risk of persistent pulmonary hypertension of the newborn is sixfold higher in neonates exposed to SSRIs after 20 weeks’ gestation .
This translates to an overall pulmonary hypertension risk of less than 1 case in 100 exposed newborns .
A population-based cohort study of 1.6 million pregnancies identified a twofold greater rate in exposed neonates.
This yields an estimated attributable risk of 2 cases per 1000 births .
In a study of more than 120,000 women prescribed antidepressants, an attributed risk of 1 case per 1000 births was found .
The maternal risk associated with discontinuing or tapering SSRI use during pregnancy must be weighed against marginally elevated neonatal risks .
Women who abruptly discontinue either serotonin- or norepinephrine-reuptake inhibitor therapy typically experience some form of withdrawal.
Not surprisingly, up to 30 percent of exposed neonates also
may exhibit withdrawal symptoms.
Symptoms are similar to opioid withdrawal but typically are less severe.
Neonatal SSRI withdrawal is usually self-limited, and the newborn rarely remains in the nursery more than 5 days .
Recent magnetic resonance imaging studies show brain volume differences in SSRI-exposed fetuses compared with unexposed ones .
Still, at this time, convincing evidence of long-term neurobehavioral effects of fetal exposure to these medications is lacking (Grzeskowiak, 2016; Man, 2017; Mezzacappa, 2017; Viktorin, 2017).
Some psychotropic medications pass into breast milk.
In most cases, however, levels are very low or undetectable.
Effects may be transient irritability, sleep disturbances, and colic.
Allopregnanolone.
A recent Food and Drug Administration (FDA)-approved therapeutic agent for treatment of postpartum depression is brexanolone, which is an allopregnanolone analogue.
Plasma allopregnanolone levels rise in connection with progesterone throughout pregnancy, and after childbirth these concentrations drop abruptly.
Failure of gamma-aminobutyric acid type A (GABA-A) receptors to adapt to these changes following delivery is a suggested antecedent to postpartum depression.
In small randomized trials, intravenous infusions of brexanolone significantly reduced Hamilton Rating Scale for Depression scores compared with placebo (Kanes, 2017; MeltzerBrody, 2018a).
Treatment is prohibitively expensive, and further studies are needed before its use is widely accepted.
Ketamine.
This anesthetic drug is given intravenously for refractory depression, but studies in pregnant or postpartum women are lacking.
Similarly, the recent FDA-approved esketamine nasal spray has not been studied in these women.
Electroconvulsive Therapy.
This form of depression treatment is occasionally necessary during pregnancy for women with major mood disorders unresponsive to pharmacotherapy.
Women undergoing electroconvulsive therapy (ECT) should be fasting for at least 6 hours.
They are given a rapid-acting antacid before the procedure, and their airway is protected to decrease the likelihood of aspiration.
After midpregnancy, a wedge is placed under the right hip to prevent sudden maternal hypotension from aortocaval compression.
Other important preparatory steps include assessment of the cervix, discontinuation of nonessential anticholinergic medication, uterine and fetal heart rate monitoring, and intravenous hydration.
During the procedure, excessive hyperventilation is avoided.
In most cases, maternal and fetal heart rate and maternal blood pressure and oxygen saturation remain normal throughout the procedure.
With proper preparation, the risks to both mother and fetus appear to be reasonable .
Such therapy is relatively safe in the first trimester .
That said, adverse maternal and perinatal outcomes have followed ECT.
Balki and associates (2006) reported a pregnancy in which fetal brain damage likely was caused by sustained maternal hypotension associated with treatment of status epilepticus stimulated by ECT.
At least two extensive reviews have evaluated ECT outcomes in pregnancy.
In one, Miller (1994) found 300 cases and reported complications in 10 percent.
These included fetal arrhythmias, vaginal bleeding, abdominal pain, and self-limited contractions.
Women not adequately prepared had higher risks for aspiration, aortocaval compression, and respiratory alkalosis.
In another review, Anderson and Reti (2009) described 339 cases, undoubtedly with some homology with the earlier study.
In most cases, ECT therapy was done to treat depression, and it was 78-percent effective.
They reported a 5-percent maternal ECT-related complication rate.
The associated perinatal complication rate was 3 percent and included two fetal deaths.
In sum, we agree with Richards (2007) that ECT in pregnancy is not “low risk” and that it should be reserved for women whose severe depression is resistant to intensive pharmacotherapy.
Suicide Self-harm is a primary cause of death among women during the perinatal period, and major depression is
among the strongest predictors .
Between 2004 and 2012, self-harm, suicide, or drug overdose was the leading cause of maternal death in Colorado .
During a similar time period in Ontario, perinatal suicide accounted for 5.3 percent of all maternal deaths .
Fetal loss is associated with a threeto fivefold greater risk for suicide .
And, 54 percent of pregnancy-associated suicides reportedly involved intimate-partner conflict .
# Bipolar and Related Disorders.
According to the National Institute of Mental Health (2017a), the lifetime prevalence for manic-depression illness is 4.4 percent.
The prevalence of bipolar disorder does not vary between gravidas and nonpregnant reproductive-aged women .
It has a strong genetic component and has been linked to possible mutations on chromosomes 16 and 8 .
The risk that monozygotic twins are both affected is 40 to 70 percent, and the risk for first-degree relatives is 5 to 10 percent .
Periods of depression last at least 2 weeks.
At other times, patients are manic, in which mood is abnormally raised, expansive, or irritable.
Potential organic causes of mania include substance abuse, hyperthyroidism, and central nervous system tumors.
These are all excluded during an acute event.
Importantly, pregnancy frequently prompts medication discontinuation, which poses a substantially increased risk for relapse.
Approximately one third of patients with manic-depression illness will attempt suicide during their lifetime .
Bipolar Disorder in Pregnancy This disorder has also been associated with adverse perinatal outcomes such as preterm birth .
Women who experience pregnancy complications are more likely to exhibit periods of mania or depression .
Moreover, symptomatic women during pregnancy more likely have postpartum relapses that can be severe .
Women who tend to be manic present with exacerbations earlier in the postpartum period.
Typical therapy for bipolar disorder includes mood stabilizers such as lithium, valproic acid, and carbamazepine and antipsychotic medications .
Treatment of bipolar disorder in pregnancy is complex and is ideally managed concurrently with a psychiatrist.
Decisions include risks versus benefits of mood stabilizers, some of which are teratogenic .
For example, lithium has been linked to Ebstein anomaly in exposed fetuses.
More recent data, however, suggest a lower risk of cardiac malformations than previously indicated (Munk-Olsen, 2018; Patorno, 2017).
Nevertheless, many recommend fetal echocardiography for lithium-exposed fetuses.
Some limited evidence suggests that lithium in breast milk, when its elimination is impaired as in dehydration or immaturity, can adversely affect the infant .
However, lithium use in mothers with a healthy, term fetus is considered moderately safe.
Children born to bipolar women do not appear to suffer long-term adverse effects .
A more detailed discussion of other mood stabilizers and antipsychotic medications side effects is found in Chapter 8 (p. 153).
Postpartum Psychosis This severe mental disorder is usually a bipolar disorder, but it may be due to major depression .
Its estimated incidence is 1 case in every 1000 deliveries, and it is more common in nulliparas, especially those with obstetrical complications (Bergink, 2016; Tinkelman, 2017).
In most cases, illness manifests within 2 weeks of delivery and lasts 2 to 3 months.
Because those with underlying psychiatric disease have a 10- to 15-fold risk for recurrence postpartum, close monitoring is recommended.
Women with a history of bipolar disease typically exhibit symptoms within 1 to 2 days after delivery (Heron, 2007, 2008).
Manic symptoms include feeling excited or elated, being active or energetic, feeling “chatty,” and suffering insomnia.
Affected women may display confusion and disorientation but may also have lucid episodes.
Postpartum psychosis has a 50-percent recurrence risk in the next pregnancy.
As a result, Bergink and associates (2016) recommend initiating lithium therapy immediately after delivery in women with a history of postpartum psychosis.
The
clinical course of bipolar illness with postpartum psychosis is comparable with that for nonpregnant women.
Patients usually require hospitalization, pharmacological treatment, and long-term psychiatric care.
Psychotic women may have delusions leading to thoughts of self-harm or harm to their infants.
Unlike women with nonpsychotic depression, these women commit infanticide, albeit uncommonly .
In most instances, women with postpartum psychosis ultimately develop relapsing, chronic, psychotic manic-depression.
# Anxiety Disorders.
The prevalence of anxiety disorder in the prior year among women in the United States is 23 percent .
These relatively common disorders include panic attack, panic disorder, social anxiety disorder, specific phobia, separation anxiety disorder, and generalized anxiety disorder.
All are characterized by irrational fear, tension, and worry, which are accompanied by physiological changes such as trembling, nausea, hot or cold flashes, dizziness, dyspnea, insomnia, and frequent urination .
They are treated with psychotherapy and medication, which may be an SSRI, tricyclic antidepressant, monoamine oxide inhibitor, or other.
Anxiety Disorders in Pregnancy Despite the relatively high prevalence in childbearing-aged women, data regarding anxiety disorders in pregnancy are few.
Most reports conclude that rates between pregnant and nonpregnant women do not differ.
One analysis of 268 gravidas with generalized anxiety disorder demonstrated that both symptoms and anxiety severity decline across pregnancy .
From their review, Thorsness and colleagues (2018) concluded that some of the anxiety disorders may have important maternal-fetal implications.
Some researchers, but not all, have linked these disorders to preterm birth, fetal-growth restriction, and poor neurobehavioral development .
Children with a history of in utero exposure to maternal anxiety are felt to be at greater risk for various neuropsychiatric conditions such as attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder (ADHD).
Anxiety Disorder Treatment Anxiety disorders can be effectively treated during pregnancy with psychotherapy, cognitive behavioral therapy, or medication .
Mood and anxiety disorders coexist in more than half of women identified with either diagnosis.
Thus, antidepressants—specifically, SSRIs —listed in Table 64-3 are often the first line of pharmacotherapy.
As with other medication exposures in pregnancy, choosing a single SSRI agent at the lowest effective dose is preferred.
Benzodiazepines also are commonly used to treat anxiety or panic disorders .
Earlier case-control studies linked their use to a possible increased risk for cleft lip and palate.
A metaanalysis of more than 1 million exposed pregnancies, however, did not identify a teratogenic risk .
Benzodiazepines, especially when taken during the third trimester, can cause neonatal withdrawal syndrome, which persists for days to weeks after delivery.
Importantly, benzodiazepines should be avoided in women with current or past history of substance misuse .
Schizophrenia Spectrum Disorders.
This major form of mental illness affects 1.1 percent of adults .
Schizophrenia spectrum disorders are defined by abnormalities in one or more of the following domains: delusions, hallucinations, disorganized thinking, grossly disorganized or abnormal motor behavior, and negative symptoms.
Brain-scanning techniques such as positron emission tomography (PET) and functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) show that schizophrenia is a degenerative brain disorder.
Subtle anatomical abnormalities are present early in life and worsen with time.
Schizophrenia has a major genetic component, and concordance was 33 percent in monozygotic twins in large database .
If one parent has schizophrenia, the risk to offspring is 5 to 10 percent .
Some data, including a strong association between schizophrenia and the velocardiofacial syndrome, suggest associated genes.
Some cases are related to chromosome 22q11, but sophisticated gene mapping studies clearly show that schizophrenia is not related to a
single gene or mutation .
Other putative risks for subsequent schizophrenia in an exposed fetus remain unproven, for example, the association with maternal influenza A infection .
Signs of illness begin approximately at age 20 years, and work and psychosocial functioning typically deteriorate over time.
Women have a slightly later onset than men.
Thus, many investigators theorize that estrogen is protective.
With appropriate treatment, patients can experience a decline or cessation of symptoms.
Within 5 years from the first signs of illness, 60 percent have social recovery, 50 percent are employed, 30 percent are mentally handicapped, and 10 percent require continued hospitalization .
# Schizophrenia in Pregnancy.
Most studies have reported no adverse maternal outcomes, although some earlier ones found higher rates of low birthweight, fetal-growth restriction, and preterm delivery.
In a study of more than 3000 pregnancies in schizophrenic women, the rate of placental abruption was elevated threefold and that of “fetal distress”—vaguely defined—was increased 1.4-fold .
Because schizophrenia has a high recurrence rate if medications are discontinued, continued therapy during pregnancy is advised.
That said, “typical” antipsychotic drugs listed in Table 64-3 are associated with adverse fetal or maternal sequelae in some, but not all studies (Coughlin, 2015; Robinson, 2012).
Because less is known about “atypical” antipsychotics, the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2018c) recommends against their routine use in pregnant and breastfeeding women.
The FDA (2011) issued a safety communication concerning the potential risk for abnormal muscle movements and withdrawal symptoms in newborns of mothers treated with antipsychotic drugs during the third trimester.
Eating Disorders.
These include anorexia nervosa, in which the patient refuses to maintain normal body weight, and bulimia nervosa, in which binge eating is usually followed by purging or excessive fasting to maintain normal body weight .
Eating behavior disturbances largely affect adolescent females and young adults.
With anorexia and bulimia, the lifetime prevalence for each is 2 to 3 percent .
Bulik and coworkers (2009) studied pregnancy outcomes in almost 36,000 Norwegian women screened for eating disorders.
Approximately 0.1 percent had anorexia nervosa, 0.85 percent had bulimia nervosa, and 5.1 percent reported a binge-eating disorder.
This 6-percent pregnancy prevalence is similar to the 6-month prevalence for nonpregnant individuals .
The last subtype had a higher risk for large-for-gestational age neonates with a concomitantly increased cesarean delivery rate.
All eating disorders begin with the desire to be slim, and women with chronic eating disorders may migrate between subtypes .
# Eating Disorders in Pregnancy.
Early pregnancy complication rates are increased with both eating disorders, but especially in women with bulimia nervosa .
Generally, eating disorder symptoms improve during pregnancy, and remission rates may reach 75 percent.
In contrast, a typical case of hyperemesis gravidarum may actually be a new or relapsing case of bulimia nervosa or of binge-purge type anorexia nervosa.
As perhaps expected, anorexia is associated with low-birthweight, smaller head circumference, and small-for-gestational-age newborns .
Children born to these mothers are more likely to have psychopathology at 7 years .
Additional maternal risks associated with eating disorders include poor wound healing and difficulties with breastfeeding.
At a minimum, closely monitoring gestational weight gain in women with a suspected history of an eating disorder seems prudent.
Care for these women involves a multidisciplinary team that includes an obstetrician, mental health provider, and either dietician or nutritionist.
Psychological treatment is the cornerstone for treatment in women with eating disorders and frequently includes cognitive behavioral therapy.
Anorexia nervosa often responds to motivational interactions with meal planning .
After
delivery, women with eating disorders are more prone to postpartum depression.
Women with bulimia are at particular risk for disease rebound after delivery because of body image concerns.
Substance Use Disorders.
According to the American Psychiatric Association (2013), substancerelated disorders encompass 10 classes of drugs that include caffeine, tobacco, cannabis, hallucinogens, opioids, anxiolytics, and stimulants.
Their essential feature is a cluster of cognitive, behavioral, and physiological symptoms indicating that the individual continues to use the substance despite significant related problems.
Central to these disorders is an underlying change in brain circuits that may persist beyond detoxification and characterized by repeated relapses.
It is estimated that 10 percent of fetuses are exposed to one or more illicit drugs.
Agents may include heroin and other opiates, cocaine, amphetamines, barbiturates, and marijuana .
Well-documented sequelae include fetal-growth restriction, low birthweight, and drug withdrawal soon after birth.
Adverse effects of marijuana are being delineated with expanding legalization.
As noted by Metz and Borgelt (2018), adverse perinatal outcomes associated with marijuana use are especially seen with heavy use.
Moreover, later childhood neurobehavioral consequences may follow prenatal exposure.
Thus, women are currently advised to refrain from using marijuana during pregnancy and lactation.
Women who use such drugs frequently do not seek prenatal care, which in itself is associated with risks for preterm and lowbirthweight newborns.
# Opioid Use Disorder.
These disorders have reached epidemic proportions in the United States.
The rates of maternal opioid-related diagnoses at delivery (0.8 percent) and of neonatal abstinence syndrome (0.7 percent) in 2017 in the United States were significantly higher than those in 2010 .
Because of this, the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists and the American Society of Addiction Medicine (2017) recommend universal screening by questionnaire at the first prenatal visit.
Urine drug testing to detect or confirm substance use is performed only with patient consent and in compliance with state laws.
Medication-Assisted Treatment For women who abuse opioids, methadone maintenance can be initiated within a registered treatment program to reduce opioid use complications and narcotic withdrawal, to encourage prenatal care, and to avoid drug culture risks .
Buprenorphine also may be offered and managed by physicians with specific credentialing (Boyars, 2018; Jones, 2018).
Available programs can be found through the treatment locator of the Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration at www.samhsa.gov.
Methadone dosages usually are initiated at 10 to 30 mg daily and titrated as needed.
Concomitant chronic use of naloxone with buprenorphine is discouraged given risks of precipitating neonatal withdrawal.
Medically Supervised Withdrawal In some women, careful medication-assisted withdrawal may be an appropriate option.
This is controversial because of the relatively high relapse rate, and it is discouraged by the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists and the American Society of Addiction Medicine (2017).
From their review of more than 600 treated women, Boyars and Guille (2018) caution against this approach but concluded that assisted withdrawal is a reasonable approach.
At Parkland Hospital, pregnant opioid users who decline maintenance therapy are offered inpatient hospitalization for controlled methadone taper.
The goal is reduction of neonatal opioid withdrawal syndrome rates (Dashe, 2002; Stewart, 2013).
In 2017, 69 women who were enrolled in our opioid perinatal intervention program delivered at Parkland Hospital.
Of these women, 37 (54 percent) delivered without use of opioids at delivery.
Their neonates’ median length of stay was 4.5 days, which was significantly shorter than the 23.5 days required for newborns whose mothers were using opioids at delivery.
Neonatal Opioid Withdrawal Syndrome This is a drug
withdrawal syndrome that most commonly follows maternal opioid use.
It is discussed in Chapter 33 (p. 605).
Posttraumatic Stress Disorder.
This is included in trauma– and stressor–related disorders .
The essential feature of PTSD is development of characteristic symptoms following exposure to one or more traumatic events.
One example in obstetrics is PTSD following hyperemesis gravidarum .
Symptoms may be anxiety or fear but can be anhedonia, dysphoria, or dissociative behavior.
According to Yonkers and coworkers (2014), 8 percent of pregnant women have facets of this syndrome.
Psychotherapy is one first-line therapy .
These women are also treated with benzodiazepines or antidepressants.
Those with concordant major depression are at high risk for preterm birth.
Personality Disorders.
These disorders are characterized by the chronic use of certain coping mechanisms in an inappropriate, stereotyped, and maladaptive manner.
They are rigid and unyielding personality traits.
The American Psychiatric Association (2013) recognizes three clusters of personality disorders: 1. Paranoid, schizoid, and schizotypal personality disorders, which are characterized by oddness or eccentricity.
2. Histrionic, narcissistic, antisocial, and borderline disorders, which are all characterized by dramatic presentations along with self-centeredness and erratic behavior.
3. Avoidant, dependent, compulsive, and passive-aggressive personalities, which are characterized by underlying fear and anxiety.
In the United States, the prevalence of any personality disorder in the past year approximates 9 percent .
Genetic and environmental factors are thought important in their genesis.
Psychotherapy is appropriate treatment, but most affected individuals do not recognize their problem, and thus only 20 percent seek help.
In an observational study of 202 women with borderline personality disorder, De Genna and associates (2012) noted that affected women become pregnant during the most severe trajectory of their illness.
They are at higher risk for adolescent and unintended pregnancies.
Notably, Conroy and coworkers (2010) found that a mother’s ability to care for her newborn was impaired only when a personality disorder was coupled with depression.